<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word from the Lord to the priests of England in general that teach for hire</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1545</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14008</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13588534</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13588534</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27142)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 783:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word from the Lord to the priests of England in general that teach for hire</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: W. Baily.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Probable place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100608:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100608:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
            <head>A WORD From the LORD To the PRIESTS OF ENGLAND In General that teach for HIRE.</head>
            <p>HEar O ye Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> the word of the Lord God as it came unto me in the year, 1659. the ſixth moneth, the twenty fifth clay of the moneth; ſaying,</p>
            <p>Thus ſaith the Lord God, Ile make you a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to your ſelves, and one to another, and Ile ſtrike you with amazements and fears, and bring everlaſting ſhame upon you, and you ſhal be a hilling, and a bye word to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and a diriſion to Generations, for as much as you have refuſed and rejected the day of your viſitation, my witneſſe in you ſhall condemn you, and my power ſhall ſhake you, and make your hearts to melt and tremble at my dreadful preſence, ye that have been a terror to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and a burthen, and oppreſſors of my dear Children and Servants, which in my pure power was moved to warn you <hi>to flee from the wrath to come,</hi> you ſhall be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, burthened, and terrified, and there will be none
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100608:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
to deliver you, for he that ſhould be your deliverer, will be your eternal condemnation, therefore wo be to you, O ye proud prophane hirelings of <hi>England,</hi> your day is haſtening, wherein your perpetual ſhame, contempt and miſery ſhall be made manifeſt to thouſands; have you not been long leaders of the people, and called your ſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel? but the Goſpel which is my <hi>power</hi> ſaith the Lord God ſhall grinde you to powder, and have you not cauſed the people to erre from the knowledge of my way (the <hi>light in every mans conſcience, which ſhews them ſin and evil?</hi>) and have you not riſen up with an open mouth againſt my Son, Chriſt, <hi>the Light,</hi> which lighteth every man that cometh into the World? and have you not blaſphemed my Holy Name, and cauſed many of my dear and tender children to ſuffer grievous burthens and reproaches, perſecutions, and long impriſonments, by crying out errors, deceivers, ſeducers, and blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? but as I live ſaith the Lord God, theſe things which you have ſwallowed down, ſhal you vomit up again, and if none of you will yet bow down to my witneſſe the <hi>Light</hi> in you, which lets you ſee the evil of your waies, you ſhall become the apparenteſt example of my wrath &amp; indignation, as hath not been known in many ages; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any of you ſhal yet conſider the end of your waies, and ſpeedilie repent and turn from your evil deeds and words, and confeſſe to my Son, <hi>the true Light</hi> which you have ſo long done deſpite unto, it may be ſuch may be hid in the terrible day at hand; for thus ſaith the Lord God, even the Lord of hoſts, my determination is to break to pieces, confound, root up, and overturn, deſtroy, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie conſume the very ſavour of your root, &amp; that earth (or earthly power) which ſtrives to uphold you, ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of your plagues, I the Lord have ſpoken it, and in mine eternal Councel it ſhall be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>Therefore O ye Prieſts, conſider; Was not their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and folly made manifeſt, that withſtood the truth in ages paſt? Or did ever any weapon formed (or Law, plot or decree) againſt it and them that were in it, proſper? and is not Chriſt Jeſus the truth, <hi>who lighteth every man that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100608:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
cometh into the world?</hi> and are not they in the truth which be in the light which he hath enlightened them withall? and have you not withſtood this truth, and them that be in it by reproaches, revilings, perſecutions, ſpoiling of goods, and impriſonments, more cruel and violent then <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes?</hi> Let Gods witneſſe anſwer, which lets you ſee your ungodly deeds, and hard ſpeeches, and convinceth you ſecretly of them, when you are alone and heeds it; but you are filling up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of your Fathers, that upon you may be powred down the vengeance <hi>for all the righteous blood ſhed from Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias to this day,</hi> and you ſhall not proceed any further, for then ſhall your folly, madneſſe, and wickedneſſe, be manifeſt to all men as theirs was; Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God of power, howl, howl, and lament, O ye Idol ſhepherds, and be aſhamed of your work O ye ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vinedreſſers, my fury is exceedingly kindled againſt you, and I am even wearie with forbearing; is not your flocks like the wild beaſts of the foreſt, and your grapes of the vine of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and your gardens grown over with thorns, hiſtles, and nettles? who of my Lambs and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren can come among you, and not be torn, puſht or rent? Who of my Servants have I ſent in my power among you that have not ſuffered violence by you, either by your bloodie hands, or by your arrowes ſhot at them, even bitter and reproachful words? let my witneſſe ſearch you and bow down ſpeedily before it, leaſt ye utterly fall into my Almighty dreadful hands where you will be plagued and tormented day and night for ever and ever without end; for my decree is gone forth concerning you, (and its revealed to babes) that night is come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you (who have withſtood the pure day of light and life in which the Son of man is come as a thief, and ſo you like <hi>Judas</hi> and his company are riſen againſt him with ſwords and ſtaves, <hi>he that readeth, let him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, hear the word of the Lord, O ye treacherous Prieſts, double minded, unſtable, ungodly, truce-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, heady, high-minded, who have long loved plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100608:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
and eaſe in the fleſh more then the pure God or his righteous way of life, your day of perplexity and wo is at hand, and you ſhall not eſcape.</p>
            <p>For thus ſaith the Lord God, your horſes nature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor your horſes without, ſhal not deliver you from my decreed purpoſe, your ſword within and without, ſhall be your ſnare, and you ſhall fall like the handful after the harveſt man, and be driven like chaffe before the wind, <hi>for blood-thirſty and deceitful men ſhall not live out halfe their dayes,</hi> hear and underſtand; no murtherers have eternal life, and the wickeds ſword ſhall enter into his own bowels, hear ye Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> this I charge upon you, to whom it is, who have taken my Servants words into your prophane lips, ſaying, <hi>ſome truſt in horſes, and ſome in chariots, but we will truſt in the Name of the Lord our God;</hi> are ye not here found deceitful, and with a lie in your right hand, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of falſhood, and a ſeed of evil doers, who truſt in the arm of fleſh, and to it ſtil have fled for your maintenance, and been found fighters againſt the true and living God, and his Children, for your God which now is manifeſt to be your bellies to thouſands, for upon your bellies have you ſtill gone, and duſt have you eat, and with it have you fed the people, and not with life, nor underſtanding in my Councel (the light which they be lighted withal) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have you awakned my witnes in the hearts of them, but in ignorance, eaſe, and unrighteouſneſs have you lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to lie down to ſleep and ſlumber with them; and are the blind dumb dogs that have not barked (to wit ſpake in my pure power) to awaken and anſwer my own the juſt in every one, whereby the thief and robber might have been ſeen in <hi>the light the éye,</hi> which none ſees you all to be thieves, murtherers, and robbers, that have climbed up another way then by the door Chriſt <hi>(who lighteth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the world)</hi> and have built upon the ſand, but the ſtorms are riſing apace, that wil ſhake you off the earth, wherein great will be your fall, and you ſhall never riſe again ſaith the Lord God Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>VVritten by a Servant of the Lord at <hi>Wellingborrow</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re,</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. Baily.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100608:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
